Mss.Rec.30 Mss.Rec.30
American Philosophical Society
Tlingit and Yakutat songs
March-August 1954
Mss.Rec.30
American Philosophical Society
10.0 Tape(s)
Recordings made in Yakutat, Alaska in 1954. Includes personal songs, mourning songs, drinking songs, love songs, shaman songs, and children's songs. Most songs are Tlingit, with some of Haida, Ahtna, and Southern Tutchone origin.
10 sound tape reels (9 hr., 3 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in.
De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004
Related Archival Materials
See also Frederica de Laguna, Recordings at Yakutat, Alaska (Rec. 19).
General note
Content, notes on songs, and classification of songs in No. 30 (N2.3a, N2.3b and N2.3c), APS Yearbook, 1954: 179.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Frederica De Laguna, 1959.
Conditions Governing Access
Permission required for access to materials. Please consult the Manuscripts Librarian for details.
Bigoraphical/Historical note
Frederica de Laguna, an archaeologist and anthropologist, studied Alaskan native cultures.
Indians of North America--Alaska--Music; Songs.; Sound recordings; Tlingit Indians--Music; Yakutat Tlingit Tribe
- Audio recordings
  - Peace Song for Jenny White's mother; to tl'ukwaXAdi-yAtx'i, 1954-03-23; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:12; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; White, Charley; White, Jenny
    Scope and Contents note
    "Jenny White explains in Tlingit how her brother and uncle died of whiskey given by the tl'ukwaXAdi, and how her mother had been taken as peace officer. This song was composed for her. Date about 1901. [It is a Dry Bay song.]" Ends with idenfitication of the song by Frederica de Laguna. Sung together by Charley White and Jenny White.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Dance Song composed by Dry Bay Chief George about Kardeetoo; to gIneXqwan-yATx'i, 1954-03-23; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:07; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; White, Charley; White, Jenny
    "Charley White explains in Tlingit that this song was composed by the tl'uknaXAdi in honor of his grandfather's nephew, Kardetoo, who invited the Dry Bay people to a potlatch in Yakutat. [The potlatch was for Mud Shark House. Karedtoo's mother's father was tl'uknaXAdi. Date 1911.]" Ends with idenfitication of the song by Frederica de Laguna, in which song is mistakenly said to have been given by Kardetoo to his guests. Sung together by Charley White and Jenny White.
    Potlatch--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Shaman's Song of tek'-ic, 1954-03-23; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:39; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; White, Charley
    Song is preceded by Charley White's explanation in Tlingit that he is going to sing the spirit cong of his father's older brother, lXagusa [or tek'-ic]. Song is followed by repetition of the words of the song in Tlingit. "The spirit is that of the teqwedi hero, lucwAq, and is called lucwAq yek or laXak'ina yek 'Spirit on top of Yakutat.'"
    Shamanism--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit Indians--Religion; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Hymn in Tlingit and in English, 1954-03-23; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:28; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; White, Maggy
    Hymns; Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Love Song composed by X'adanek' for his wife; teqwedi-yAtx'i, 1954-04-08; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:32; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie; White, Charley
    Recording begins with Charley White introducing the song in Tlingit, "explaining that his father used to like drink, and also liked teqwedi-yAtx'i as much as liquor. [X'adanek' died in 1888.]" Sung together by Charley White and miniie Johnson.
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Love songs; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Story and Song of Drum House teqwedi's Golden Eagle, 1954-04-08; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:19; Abraham, Olaf; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; James, Sheldon; White, Charley
    Begins with story of Golden Eagle, told by Olaf Abraham. Song is then sung by Olaf Abraham and Charley White. Story is the retold Olaf and translated into English by Sheldon James. Ends with explanation of recording by Frederica de Laguna.
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit Indians--Folklore; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Olaf Abraham's Song about Antlen River, 1954-04-08; 01-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:25; Abraham, Olaf; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; James, Sheldon
    Begins with Olaf speaking in Tlingit, "explaining how he composed the song when fishing at Antlen. [1953. Apparently the second stanza was just recently composed.]" Ends with identification of song by Frederica de Laguna.
    Antlen River (Alaska)--Songs and music; Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Olaf Abraham's Wolf Call Song to his wife; to kagwantan-yAtx'i, 1954-04-08; 01-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:28; Abraham, Olaf; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004
    Begins with Olaf's explanation in Tlingit that the song was composed in 1939 because his wife wept when he left her to go trapping. Ends with identification of song by Frederica de Laguna.
  - Olaf Abraham's Song, to kagwantan-yAtx'i, 1954-04-08; 01-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:37; Abraham, Olaf; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
    "[Song] was composed in 1946 when Olaf Abraham's brother-in-law, Young George Bremner, was drowned; and when his former wife had to go to the hospital for an operation." Ends with identification of song by Frederica de Laguna.
  - Peace Song for Mrs. Situk Jim; to teqwedi-yAtx'i, 1954-04-08; 01-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:14; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie; Sampson, Blind
    "Mrs. Situk Jim, Xosal-tla, was miniie's older half-sister. She was taken as peace-officer at the time her son killed Jenny Jack's mother. Mrs. Situk Jim died in 1916. The song was composed by Blind Sampson."
  - Mourning Song about the Crane Boat (claimed by both tl'uknaXadi and kwack'qwan), (1 verse only), 1954-04-09; 01-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:34; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Dick, Frank; White, Charley
    In introductory explanation to song, Charley White refers to defeat of tl'uknaXAdi by ganAXtedi- probably at Chilkat.
  - Drinking Song of Clarence Peterson, to tl'uknaXAdi-yAtx'i, 1954-04-09; 01-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:12; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Dick, Frank; Peterson, Clarence; White, Charley
    Ends with identification of song and previous song by Frederica de Laguna. Charley White explains in Tlingit that the composer of the song, who died in 1941, was addressing his wife.
    Drinking songs--Alaska; Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - John Ellis tells story of daXodzu, 1954-03-25; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:53; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ellis, John
    Text identified by Frederica de Laguna at end of subsequently recorded story. See Related Recording.
    Tlingit Indians--Folklore; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - John Ellis tells story about lket'titc, 1954-03-25; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:55; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ellis, John
    Recording ends with identification by Frederica de Laguna of this text and the preceding story. See Related Recording.
  - Incomplete version of Situk Train song, 1954-05-03; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:51; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Chester, Mrs.
    Complete version of song given in subsequent recording. See Related Recording.
  - Blind Sampson's song about Situk Train, composed for Kardeetoo; to teqwedi'yAtxi'i, 1954-05-03; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:18; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Chester, Mrs.; Sampson, Blind; White, Charley
    Recording ends with identification of song by Frederica de Laguna. Incomplete version of song was previously given. See Related Recording.
  - Litya Bay George's Song to the Bears; to X'at'k'a-ayi-yAtx'i, 1954-05-03; 02-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:28; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Chester, Mrs.; White, Charley; White, Jenny
    "Mrs. C. Johnson introduces her father's song. He had been chased by bears, his father's totem animals, when hunting." Recording ends with identification of song by Frederica de Laguna.
    Bears; Hunting songs; Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Blind Dave's Song to Jenny Dick and to Lituya Bay George; to cAnkuqedi-yAtx'i and kagwantan-yAtx'i, 1954-05-03; 02-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:30; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Chester, Mrs.; White, Jenny
    Song composed in 1914 to Blind Dave's daughter, Jenny Dick, who died in 1912 in Seattle. The first stanza is addressed to her; the second to Lituya Bay George, Mrs. C Johnson's father. Song introduced by Mrs. C. Johnson in Tlingit. Recording ends with identification of song by Frederica de Laguna.
  - Dry Bay George's Song for dek'ina House, 1954-05-31; 02-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:32; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; George, Annie
    Recording ends with identification of song by Frederica de Laguna.
  - Athabaskan Ptarmigan Dance Song, 1954-06-10; 02-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:17; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Chester, Mrs.
    A song belonging to the tl'uknaXadi, used at potlatches.
    Potlatch--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Social life and customs; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Mrs. Chester Johnson's Song to her son; to Norwegian-yAtx'i, 1954-06-10; 02-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:55; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Chester, Mrs.
    "Song composed a few days before."
  - Athabaskan Drinking Song, 1954-06-10; 02-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:56; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Chester, Mrs.
    A song from Klukwan, first heard by the singer in 1914. This song is identified by Frederica de Laguna and the end of the subsequently recorded song. See Related Recording.
    Athapascan Indians--Alaska--Music; Drinking songs--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Athabaskan Drinking Song, 1954-06-10; 02-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:26; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Chester, Mrs.
    Recording ends with identification of this song and the previously recorded song. See Related Recording. Collector identifies words of song as being Athabascan and having been given by Indians at Klukshu to cInkuqedi. The specific Athabascan language is not identified. Most likely Southern Tutchone.
    Athapascan Indians--Alaska--Music; Athapascan languages; Drinking songs--Alaska; Southern Tutchone language; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Story and Song about the Frog Screen, 1954-05-07; 02-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:22; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; George, Annie; Italio, Frank
    Story and song of how the tl'uknaxAdi found the Frog. Song composed by Dry Bay Chief George, probably in 1910. For translation, see first item under Related Recording. Song was later re-recorded. For later recording, see second item under Related Recording.
    Frogs--Folklore; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit Indians--Folklore; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Translation of Tlingit story, 1954-05-07; 02-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:47; Bremner, Helen; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004
    Translation of "Story and Song about the Frog Screen." See Related Recording.
    Frogs--Folklore; Tlingit Indians--Folklore; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Shaman's Song, 1954-05-07; 02-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:19; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank
    "This is a spirit song belonging to the shaman, gutcda, and refers to Xat-qwani, Fish-People Spirits."
  - Shaman's Song, 1954-05-07; 02-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:51; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank
    "This song is also one belonging to gutcda and refers to the Xat-qwani. Not sure that it is not another stanza of [previous] song."
  - Raven Story and Songs, 1954-05-07; 02-16; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:48; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank
    Story of approximately 10 minutes in Tlingit about Raven, followed by two songs about Raven stealing Box of Daylight. Tape runs out before completion of second song.
    Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit Indians--Folklore; Tlingit language; Tlingit mythology; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Kagwantan Mourning Song (incorrect version), 1954-03-27; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:55; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ellis, Emma
    Singer requested to record the song a second time. (See first link under Related Recording.) Recording identified by Frederica de Laguna as at end of subsequent recording. (See second link under Related Recording.)
    Mourning customs--United States--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Seltin's Marriage Song, 1954-03-27; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:29; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ellis, Emma
    Marriage; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Song sung after passing safely under the Alsek ice, 1954-03-27; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:09; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ellis, Emma
    "Emma Ellis introduces the song in Tlingit. It is an old tlukwaXAdi song, apparently sung by Emma's father's mother's brother." Recording ends with identification of song and two previously recorded songs. See Related Recording.
    Alsek River; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Kagwantan Mourning Song (correct version), 1954-04-01; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:31; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ellis, Emma
    "Emma Ellis introduces song in Tlingit. It was supposedly composed by cacken, a kagwantan survivor of the war with the cX'atqwan of Wrangell. The latter were finally massacred at a peace dance given by the kagwantan at Sitka about the middle of the last century. Cf. Swanton Song 103." Second recorded version of song. For first version, see Related Recording. Recording ends with identification of song by Frederica de Laguna.
    Mourning customs--United States--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Blind Dave's deathbed song to his young wife; to kagwantan-yAtx'i, 1954-04-01; 03-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:13; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ellis, Emma
    Song composed by the singer's father's uncle's sons--a classificatory brother. He was the son of gutcda, the Dry Bay shaman. It is addressed to his young wife. Song introuduced by Emma Ellis in Tlingit.
    Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Rites and ceremonies; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Emma Ellis' Own Song; to teqwedi-yAtxi'i and kagwantan-yAtx'i, 1954-05-11; 03-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:07; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Ellis, Emma
    "Emma Ellis introduces the song in Tlingit. She composed it in 1907 when she was 11 years olds, when her father and mother drowned. The first stanza refers to her father's death; the second stanza is addressed to her dead husband and was composed about 1913; the third stanza was improvised on the spot and sung to FdeL."
    Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Fanny William's Song; to tl'uknaXadi-yAtx'i, 1954-05-16; 03-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:41; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Chester, Mrs.; Peterson, Louise; Williams, Fanny
    "Louise Peterson introduces the song. It is said to have been composed in Sitka, and later introduced to Yakutat about 1916. Louise's 'cousin' Fanny Williams sang the song a few hours before she died."
  - Peace Song for Frank Italio, 1954-05-07; 03-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:10; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank
    "This is the song to which he danced when serving as a peace officer."
  - CAnkuqedi Coming-in Song, 1954-05-07; 03-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:30; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank
    A song used by Frank Italio's sibling when entering a house to which they had been invited as guests to a potlatch. Song is described as "lacking words" but also being in "Dry Bay Athabaskan"--most likely Southern Tutchone.
    Athapascan Indians--Alaska--Music; Potlatch--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - cAnkuqedi Dance Song, 1954-05-07; 03-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:22; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank
    Identified by collector as possibly coming from Athabascan Indians at Dry Bay.
    Athapascan Indians--Alaska--Music; Potlatch--Alaska; Tlingit dance; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Similar Dance Song, 1954-05-07; 03-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:03; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank
  - cAnkuqedi Sitting Down Song, 1954-05-07; 03-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:02; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank
    Collector identifies song as "apparently one used by guests at a potlatch when they are seated."
  - cAnkuqedi Sitting Down Song, 1954-05-07; 03-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:27; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank
    A song acquired by Dry Bay people, at marriage of a women from nuqwa on headwaters of Alsek.
  - Sitka Peace Officer's Song in 3 parts; to Xas'hItan-yAtx'i and t'inedi-yAtx'i, 1954-05-07; 03-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:05; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank
  - Song for the Haven Post, 1954-05-17; 03-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:24; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Dick, Frank, Mrs.
    "It is a very old [song] belonging to the tl'uknaXAdi."
  - Teasing Song for a Boy (about Raven Women), 1954-05-23; 03-16; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:24; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
    "This song can be used to a baby boy, or as a funny song at a peace ceremony."
    Children's songs; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Rites and ceremonies; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Teasing Song for a Girl, 1954-05-23; 03-17; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:40; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
    "This song is supposedly sung for her 'grand-children' Becky and Beverly Bremner. Since they are kagwantan-yAtx'i, the names of Leslie Milton and Susan Abraham are mentioned in the song, since these women are also kagwantan-yAtx'i."
    Children's songs; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Blind Dave's Song when his brother & nephew died, 1954-05-23; 03-18; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:33; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; George, Annie
    A song composed by Blind Dave of Dry Bay when his younger brother and his nephew were poisoned by whisky in one day.
  - Pet Song for their Children, 1954-05-23; 03-19; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:31; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; George, Annie
  - Interview between FdeL, Mrs. Katy Dixon Isaacs, and her grandson, Sheldon James Junior, 1954-03-29; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:51; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Isaacs, Katy Dixon; James, Sheldon
    Interview followed by "Mourning Song of guditlt'a who shot his younger brother." Interview continues, follwed by "kwack'qwan song for walking over the glacier."
  - Copper River Dance Song, 1954-03-29; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:16; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Isaacs, Katy Dixon; James, Sheldon
    Song followed by explanation. Song is used by the kwack'qwan.
  - F de L's Tlingit song, 1954-05-21; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:01; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004
    Song composed by Frederica de Laguna, with help from native consultants, inspiried by the song of the golden-crowned sparrow.
  - B. A. Jack's Song for the 1931 ANB Convention in Yakutat, 1954-04-25; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:59; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Thomas, Mary
    Alaska Native Brotherhood. Convention; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Kitty Martin's Song; to tl'uknaXAdi-yAtx'i and gIneXqwan-yAtx'i, 1954-04-25; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:52; Bremner, Helen; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Peterson, Louise; Thomas, Mary
    "The song was composed by Kitty Martin, sister of Louise Peterson & Mary Thomas, just before her death in 1920. It is addressed--at least the 2 first verses are--to Sheldon James Sr., with whome she was kin love, but who married another woman." Recording identified by Frederica de Laguna at end of subsequent recording. See Related Recording.
  - Kardeetoo's Song about diyagnuagt, 1954-04-25; 05-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:01; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Milton, Nick; Thomas, Mary
    "The song was composed by Kardeetoo when he built Bear Paw House at Lost River, about 1918. He mourns his dead uncles at diyagunaEt on Lost River." Recording identified by Frederica de Laguna at end of subsequent recording. See Related Recording.
  - Killerwhale Drum Song of teqwedi sib, 1954-04-25; 05-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:06; Abraham, Olaf; Bremner, Helen; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Isaacs, Katy Dixon; Milton, Nick; Peterson, Louise
    Sung with Nick Milton on the drum, Olaf calling the words, and Katy Dixon and Louise Peterson assisting. Olaf Abraham speaks in Tlingit about the song. Helen Bremner then translates Olaf's words. "It is an old [song], belonging to the Teqwedi, and was sung at potlatches, when the Killerwhale Drum was beaten. The drum was made at diyagnuaEt on Lost River and was last seen in 1921. A member of the opposite moiety was hired to beat it." This song was later re-recorded with correction. (For later version, see first item under Related Recording.) Recording identified by Frederica de Laguna at end of subsequent recording. (See second item under related Related Recording.)
    Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Raven and Snipes Song, 1954-04-25; 05-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:06; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Isaacs, Katy Dixon; Milton, Nick; Peterson, Louise; Thomas, Mary
    "A funny song, supposedly one to which Raven and Snipes danced at potlatch given by Killerwhales." Recording identified by Frederica de Laguna at end of subsequent recording. See Related Recording.
    Potlatch; Raven (Legendary character); Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Tlingit mythology; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Raven and Mussels, 1954-04-25; 05-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:07; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Isaacs, Katy Dixon; Milton, Nick; Peterson, Louise; Thomas, Mary
    Recording identified by Frederica de Laguna at end of subsequent recording. See Related Recording.
    Raven (Legendary character); Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit Indians--Folklore; Tlingit language; Tlingit mythology; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Max Italio's Love Song; to tl'uknaXAdi-yAtx'i, 1954-04-25; 05-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:30; Bremner, Helen; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Max
    "The song is addressed to his girl friend, Mrs. Ned James, Sheldon James Senior's mother. The second verse is said properly to have been addressed to one of the shaman, gutcda's, daughters." Recording ends with Frederica de Laguna's idenitification of this song and the five previously recorded song. See Related Recordings.
  - Mrs. Chester Johnson's Song to cAnkuqedi-yAtx'i and teqwedi-yAtx'i, 1954-04-29; 05-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:43; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Chester, Mrs.
    "[Song] was composed when her first husband, Clarence Peterson, died." Recording identified by Frederica de Laguna at end of subsequent recording. See Related Recording.
  - Mrs. Chester Johnson's Song to teqwedi-yAtx'i, yAnyedi-yAtx'i, and cAnkuqedi-yAtx'i, 1954-04-29; 05-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:45; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Chester, Mrs.